Kiran Shah

MECHANICAL SALES & DESIGN ENGINEER

Hatfield, PA - Email me on Indeed: indeed.com/r/Kiran-Shah/b92783de1d3a3be9

Highly skilled Mechanical Engineer who simultaneously fulfills two major roles: Lead Sales Engineer, providing a complete Sales Proposal to Customer in response to Request for Quote (RFQ), integrating all sales effort including mechanical, structural and electrical components of the bid and also act as Lead Mechanical Applications Engineer, providing product design calculations, mechanical engineering expertise, sizing and quantity estimation of the equipment. Specializes in bulk material handling equipment including Hydraulic machinery for the Power and Mining industries. Has been Lead Sales Engineer and Mechanical Applications Engineer on national and global projects of up to \$25 million. Familiar with applicable local and statutory codes. Ensures that best design practices is applied during front end to allow for competitive local and global procurement and construction. Collaborates with vendors to ensure that project purchased equipment meets requirements. Core capabilities include:

- Sales strategy development
- Timeline management for Customers contact
- Vendor collaboration & procurement activityf
- Cross-functional Team support/coordination
- Insightly/ERP system data management
- Sales Proposal development/submission
- Booking/obtaining of Sales orders
- Sales Order execution & Customer service
- Field support & assistance
- Vendor opportunity developement
- Project Design/Engineering & Cost estimation
- Technical Specification/Data preparation

Authorized to work in the US for any employer

WORK EXPERIENCE

Applications Engineer

Demco Automation - Quakertown, PA - May 2015 to Present

Responsibilities

- As an Applications Engineer, review customer requirement for shop machinery automation, generate initial cocept design, send the inquiries to sub-suppliers for buy-out items, cost estimation, compilation of total project cost, submission of the Sales proposal to Customer.
- Collaborate with vendors to ensure that project purchased equipment meets requirements.
- Respond to post bid questions/clarifications and attend follow-up meetings with customers in obtaining Sales orders/contract.

Design Engineer- Level-4

FMC Technologies Inc. - Chalfont, PA - October 1996 to January 2015

Responsibilities:

• As a Lead Sales Engineer, review customer RFQ(s) requirement, define scope of the proposal, initiate action plan for different departments within the company, send the inquiries to sub-suppliers for buy-out items, cost estimation, compilation of total project cost, monitor and manage overall sales effort for timely submission of the Sales proposal to Customer. Also manage and organize a high volume workload.

- · Coordinate and monitor structural and electrical components of the proposal.
- Collaborate with vendors to ensure that project purchased equipment meets requirements.
- Participate in senior management bid review meetings, explaining and defining costs such that profit margins can be determined.
- Prepare Technical Specification/Data sheets and submission of Sales Proposal to customer for bulk material handling system equipment such as belt conveyors, belt feeders, apron feeders, hydraulic machinery, travelling trippers.
- Respond to post bid questions/clarifications and attend follow-up meetings with customers in closing the deal and obtaining Sales orders/contract.
- As a Lead Mechanical Applications Engineer, provide product design calculations, technical expertise in mechanical application engineering, quantity estimation, technical review of design and sizing calculations associated with bulk material handling equipment provided by various sub-suppliers including:

Hydraulic Drives
Hydraulic Powerpacks
Hydraulic Couplings
Hydraulic take-ups
Pumps and hoses
Pulleys & Belting
Shafts, Seals & Bearings
Centralized Lubrication systems
Motion control products
Position control devices
Belt Scales

Vibrating Feeders

Air Ventilation Systems

Dust Suppression Systems

Dust Collection Systems

Material Sampling Systems

Stackers/Reclaimers

Barge Unloaders/Loaders

- Acted as Lead Sales and Mechanical Engineer for the following selected major projects:
- Mina Ministro Hales Expansion Project, Chile, South America, 2011. Copper ore handling for Codelco.
- Gaby Plant Phase 2, Chile, South America, 2009. Copper ore handling for Codelco.
- Cliffside Unit 5 and 6 Power Project, Cliffside, North Carolina, 2007. Coal and Limestone Handling System for Shaw Stone and Webster Inc.
- Cheswick Power Project, Springdale, Pennsylvania, 2006-2007. Limestone and Gypsum Handling System for Washington Group.
- Huntley Power Project, Tonawanda, New York, 2005-2006. Coal Handling System for NRG Energy. Was Lead Mechanical Engineer for a complete turnkey execution of the Coal Handling System including design calculations, engineering and erection/testing/commissioning of the equipment at the job site.
- Indian River Power Project, Indian River, Delaware, 2005. Coal Handling System for NRG Energy.
- Asheville Power Project, Arden, North Carolina, 2003-2004. Limestone Handling System for Parsons E & C.
- Springerville Unit-3 Power Project, Springerville, Arizona, 2003. Limestone Handling System for Bechtel Corporation.

- Springerville Unit-3 Power Project, Springerville, Arizona, 2001-2002. Coal Handling System for Bechtel Corporation.
- Was active Mechanical Engineer for the following projects:
- Millmerran Power Project, Australia, 1999-2000. Coal Handling System for Bechtel Corporation.
- Meizhou Wan Power Project, China, 1997-1998. Coal Handling System for Bechtel Corporation.

EDUCATION

Graduate Diploma Degree in Marketing Management

SARDAR PATEL UNIVERSITY, India - Vallabh Vidyanagar, Gujarat

Bachelor of Science in Mechanical Engineering (BSME)

SARDAR PATEL UNIVERSITY, India - Vallabh Vidyanagar, Gujarat

SKILLS

- System Design Mechanical Engineering •Cost Estimation •Cross-functional Teams •Sub-supplier Coordination •Management Presentations •Technical Specifications Preparation •Data Sheet Preparation
- •Proposal Submission •Customer Collaboration •Project Execution •Microsoft Word •Microsoft Excel
- •Outlook •Insightly Data management •AutoCAD .

LINKS

http://www.linkedin.com/in/kiranshah1

AWARDS

Active participation in the Meizhou Wan Power Project, Republic of China

June 2001

Provided by FMC Corporation

CERTIFICATIONS

AutoCAD 2015 Essentials.

October 2014 to Present

Issued by AUTODESK - Synergis Technologies, Quakertown, PA

Workplace Harassment

August 2014 to Present

Issued by FMC Technologies.

Company Compliance Program – Commitment to Ethics

August 2014 to Present

Issued by FMC Technologies.

Seminar on "Galvanize It"

June 2009 to Present

Issued by American Galvanizers Association.

Foreign Corrupt Practices Act with UK Bribery Summary

August 2014 to Present Issued by FMC Technologies.

PUBLICATIONS

Marketing of Material Handling Equipment

May 1984

Dissertation submitted to Sardar Patel University during the Graduate Diploma Degree course in Marketing Management.